{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In 1908, Joseph Szombathy discovered a faceless depiction of this figure in the village of Willendorf. A Velazquez painting of this figure looking back at herself in a mirror was attacked by suffragette Mary Richardson. In another painting, this figure is blown by Zephyrus to shore and stands on a giant shell. An armless statue discovered on the island of Milos depicts, for ten points, what goddess whose birth is depicted in a painting by Sandro Botticelli?",
      "answer": [
        "Venus",
        "Aphrodite",
        "Venus of Willendorf, Rokeby Venus, Venus de Milo, and/or Birth of Venus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Henry Pelham created a depiction of this event titled The Fruits of Arbitrary Power. John Adams declared that “facts are stubborn things” while successfully defending the perpetrators of this event. In Paul Revere’s depiction of this event, Thomas Preston is shown deliberately ordering an attack on a gathered crowd. Crispus Attucks was killed in, for ten points, what 1770 event in which British soldiers fired on civilians in Massachusetts?",
      "answer": [
        "Boston Massacre",
        "Incident on King Street"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This country was forced to give up its holdings in Estonia in the Second Treaty of Bromsebro. Germany occupied this country in just 6 hours in Operation Weserubung [VAY-ser-OO-bung]. In 1864, this country was invaded by Prussia, forcing it to give up Schleswig and Holstein. Margaret I united this country with Norway and Sweden to form the Kalmar Union. For ten points, name this country that, during World War II, did not oppose a German invasion in fear that they would bomb Copenhagen.",
      "answer": "Denmark"
    },
    {
      "question": "When observing Saturn, this scientist claimed to see two “ears” that were later shown to be its rings. This author of Two New Sciences and Dialogue Concerning the Two Chief World Systems discovered the phases of Venus and the four largest moons of Jupiter, a set that he now names. For ten points, name this Italian scientist who was put under house arrest by the Roman Inquisition for professing the Copernican heliocentric theory.",
      "answer": [
        "Galileo Galilei",
        "either",
        "both names"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man formulated the “eight-point regulation” to make politicians “do real work” and “say real things.” In The Governance of his country, this politician wrote about combating corruption as well as the Belt and Road Initiative. In 2018, this man spearheaded the removal of Presidential term limits from his country’s constitution. Hu Jintao was succeeded by, for ten points, what current General Secretary of the Communist Party of China?",
      "answer": "Xi Jinping"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler repudiated his marriage to Desiderata, the daughter of his rival Desiderius. A biography of this ruler by Einhard relates how he besieged and conquered Pavia, after which he took the title of King of the Lombards. Leo III urged this man to restore his authority from Roman conspirators, leading to his 800 AD coronation. For ten points, name this ruler of the Franks and Holy Roman Emperor.",
      "answer": [
        "Charlemagne",
        "Charles I",
        "Charles the Great"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This President’s policies were opposed by the “Four Horseman” of the Supreme Court. Owen Robert’s vote in West Coast Hotel v. Parrish to uphold one of this President’s policies is referred to as the “switch in time that saved nine.” This President treated to “pack the court” if it didn’t support programs like the CCC and WPA. For ten points, name this President who tried to force the Supreme Court to support the New Deal.",
      "answer": [
        "Franklin Delano Roosevelt",
        "FDR"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A May 2019 article detailed how overcrowding caused eleven people to die while performing this action, some of whom passed away at the South Col. Today, many people performing this action adjust to altitude sickness by spending several days at a base camp in Nepal. Sherpa guide Tenzing Norgay and the explorer Edmund Hillary were the first to perform, for ten points, what feat of mountaineering in the Himalayas?",
      "answer": [
        "climbing Mount Everest",
        "equivalents, such as reaching the top of Mount Everest"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man purged his rivals by using a North Korean-trained brigade that carried out the “rain that washes away the chaff.” This man’s downfall came when he removed Emmerson Mnangagwa from office, likely so he could name his wife Grace as Vice President. In 2000, land reforms by this African leader led to extreme hyperinflation. For ten points, name this head of the ZANU-PF who led Zimbabwe for 37 years.",
      "answer": "Robert Mugabe"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the prelude to this battle, two soldiers found the other side’s orders secretly wrapped around cigars. Ambrose Burnside was told to take a bridge in this battle “even if it cost 10,000 men.” In the aftermath of this battle, George McClellan was removed from command after failing to pursue Confederate forces. For ten points, name this 1862 battle in Maryland, the bloodiest single-day battle in American history.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Antietam",
        "Battle of Sharpsburg"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2009, Herman Van Rompuy was made the first permanent head of a council directing this organization. This organization was established by the Maastricht Treaty which absorbed groups led by the “Inner Six” and “Outer Seven.” In 2009, this organization passed the Treaty of Lisbon, which introduced Article 50 to its central document. The United Kingdom has attempted to leave, for ten points, what pan-national organization that includes countries like France and Germany?",
        "answer": [
          "European Union",
          "EU"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The European Union grew out of a commercial community overseeing the production of coal and this alloy of carbon and iron.",
        "answer": "steel"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these items in the British Crown Jewels is based on an example owned by Sir Tristan. A curtana is this type of weapon, as is a mythical one named Gram that was used by Sigurd to slay the dragon Fafnir. One of these weapons is taken by Sir Bedivere to the Lady of the Lake as a legendary king dies. For ten points, name these weapons, one of which was pulled from a stone by King Arthur.",
        "answer": [
          "swords",
          "Curtana before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In some myths, King Arthur legendarily pulled this sword from the stone, but most myths, including Thomas Malory’s Le Morte d’Arthur, claim he was given this sword by the Lady of the Lake.",
        "answer": "Excalibur"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this modern-day state, British forces fought the Battle of Bloody Marsh as part of the War of Jenkins” Ear. The laws of Tribal Sovereignty were established in a court case stemming from Samuel Worcester’s [WOOST-er’s] arrest in this state. George III chartered this colony to both provide a haven for debtors as well as to provide a buffer between the British colonies and Spanish-controlled Florida. For ten points, name this state founded by James Oglethorpe from Savannah.",
        "answer": "Georgia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The decision in Worcester v. Georgia was handed down by this longest-serving Chief Justice who had earlier established judicial review in Marbury v. Madison.",
        "answer": "John Marshall"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1815, Henry Salt hired Giovanni Belzoni to secure a giant statue of this man, the Younger Memnon, from his memorial temple. This ruler ordered the creation of a temple complex at Abu Simbel, partially to honor his wife Nefertari. With Mursili III, this man signed the Eternal Treaty which was meant to end his conflict with the Hittites. For ten points, name this Egyptian pharaoh who won the Battle of Kadesh in 1259 BC.",
        "answer": [
          "Ramses II",
          "Ramses the Great"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of Kadesh may have been the largest clash of these vehicles in history.",
        "answer": "chariots"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This novel was inspired by the author’s summers with Truman Persons. The Scottsboro boys” unfair trials inspired a scene in this novel in which Calpurnia sits with her employer’s children while Mayella Ewell falsely accuses a man of rape. Dill Harris visits this novel’s protagonists, who obsess over the reclusive Boo Radley while their father defends Tom Robinson. For ten points, name this novel about lawyer Atticus Finch and his children, Jem and Scout, written by Harper Lee.",
        "answer": "To Kill a Mockingbird"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In To Kill a Mockingbird, Tom Robinson is convicted by an all-white one of these groups. Powell v. Alabama overturned the Scottsboro Boys” rape convictions, partially on the grounds that these bodies had also included no African-Americans.",
        "answer": "all-white jury"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, Alvin York captured 132 soldiers leading a surprise attack on an enemy fortification. The “Lost Battalion” became encircled by enemy troops during this war’s Meuse-Argonne offensive. A document detailing a proposed German-Mexican alliance, the Zimmerman Telegram, was intercepted during this war. John Pershing led American troops nicknamed “Doughboys” in, for ten points, what war that the United States joined in 1917?",
        "answer": "World War I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The United States was led through World War I by this President who proposed his Fourteen Points during negotiations for the Treaty of Versailles.",
        "answer": "Woodrow Wilson"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man allied with France against the Ottoman Empire after his adviser, Cardinal Wolsey, signed the Treaty of London. Francis I met with this king at the Field of the Cloth of Gold. This man passed two Acts of Supremacy, making him the head of the newly formed Anglican Church, after the Pope refused to annul his marriage to Catherine of Aragon. For ten points, name this King of England, the father of Elizabeth I and husband to six wives.",
        "answer": "Henry VIII"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "For his crimes against the Church, Henry suffered this fate on the orders of Clement VIII which cast him out of the Catholic community.",
        "answer": [
          "excommunication",
          "word forms"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This actor plays a man who serves under Colonel Bagley and is given a salary of $500 a month by Omura to help Emperor Meiji destroy a class of swordsmen. In another film, this man plays a character who is tasked with carrying out an attack with a pencil detonator at the Wolf’s Lair. This actor, who starred in The Last Samurai and played Colonel Stauffenberg in 2008’s Valkyrie, has been criticized in Europe for advertising a cult. For ten points, name this prominent Scientologist and star of the Mission: Impossible series.",
        "answer": "Tom Cruise"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In Valkyrie, Cruise plays Colonel Stauffenberg, who leads a plot to assassinate this man at the Wolf’s Lair.",
        "answer": "Adolf Hitler"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Nuclear Weapons",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country whose cities of Hiroshima and Nagasaki were targeted by atomic bombs.",
          "answer": [
            "Japan",
            "Nippon",
            "Nihon"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "American President who authorized the first atomic bomb attacks.",
          "answer": "Harry Truman"
        },
        {
          "question": "J. Robert Oppenheimer-led program that developed the atomic bomb.",
          "answer": "Manhattan Project"
        },
        {
          "question": "Laboratory outside Santa Fe built for the development of nuclear weapons.",
          "answer": "Los Alamos National Laboratory"
        },
        {
          "question": "First nuclear explosion test, carried out in the New Mexico desert.",
          "answer": "Trinity test"
        },
        {
          "question": "Atoll where, in 1954, the United States tested Castle Bravo.",
          "answer": "Bikini Atoll"
        },
        {
          "question": "International relations theory that holds no country would use a nuclear bomb, out of fear of retaliation.",
          "answer": [
            "mutually assured destruction",
            "MAD"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Scientist who worked with Stanislaw Ulam to develop the hydrogen bomb.",
          "answer": "Edward Teller"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Winston Churchill",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "War in which he served as Prime Minister of the UK.",
          "answer": "World War II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country from which his troops evacuated from Dunkirk.",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term he used in 1946 to describe Soviet domination of Eastern Europe “from Stettin...to Trieste.”",
          "answer": "Iron Curtain"
        },
        {
          "question": "German city in Saxony whose brutal firebombing he authorized.",
          "answer": "Dresden"
        },
        {
          "question": "Failed military campaign that led him to resign as Lord of the Admiralty in 1915.",
          "answer": [
            "Gallipoli Campaign",
            "Dardanelles Campaign"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "King whose abdication crisis over Wallis Simpson nearly ended Churchill’s political career.",
          "answer": "Edward VIII"
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician who succeeded him as Prime Minister in 1945.",
          "answer": "Clement Attlee"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime Minister under which he served as Chancellor of the Exchequer in the late 1920s.",
          "answer": "Stanley Baldwin"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Mahatma Gandhi",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country, his homeland, whose independence he fought the British for.",
          "answer": "India"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mineral whose taxation he protested via a 24-day march to the sea.",
          "answer": "salt march"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where he established the Tolstoy Farm outside Johannesburg.",
          "answer": "South Africa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Style of non-violent protest he promoted, from the Sanskrit for “forceful truth.”",
          "answer": "satyagraha"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where he was killed and his attacker put on trial at the Red Fort.",
          "answer": "New Delhi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who assassinated him in 1948.",
          "answer": "Nathuram Godse"
        },
        {
          "question": "Series of 1930s peace conferences in which he negotiated with Lord Irwin.",
          "answer": "Round Table Conferences"
        },
        {
          "question": "Photographer who took a picture of him behind a spinning wheel in 1946.",
          "answer": [
            "Margaret Bourke-White",
            "either underlined name"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This thinker claimed that a government ruled by “crowned ruffians” would always result in “blood and ashes” in the book Agrarian Justice. This thinker responded to Edmund Burke’s Reflections on the Revolution in France in the book (20 pts)",
        "Rights of Man and claimed that it was absurd that an island could rule a (10 pts)",
        "continent in one of his pamphlets urging for American Independence. For ten points, name this author of The American Crisis and “Common Sense.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Thomas Paine"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s foreign minister was assassinated by a Buddhist preacher in the League of Blood Incident. In the Kyujo Incident, a group of generals attempted to force this man into house arrest before he could (20 pts)",
        "address the nation. This man announced his acceptance of the Joint Declaration of Powers in the Jewel Voice Broadcast. After his nation (10 pts)",
        "surrendered aboard the USS Missouri, this man was forced to renounce his divinity. For ten points, name this Emperor of Japan during World War II."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Hirohito",
        "Showa"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A ruler with this name adopted the surname “Mikhailov” before meeting with William III and traveling through Western Europe, but his tall stature made it hard to go completely unnoticed during his “Grand (20 pts)",
        "Embassy.” The first ruler with this name imposed a tax on the (10 pts)",
        "beards of the Boyars as part of his efforts to modernize Russia. For ten points, name this “great” Russian tsar who established a large port city on the Baltic Sea."
      ],
      "answer": "Peter the Great or Peter I"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Charles Krauthammer defined a doctrine named for this politician in the wake of withdrawing from the ABM treaty. In a 1995 election, this politician defeated Ann Richards with the help of (20 pts)",
        "Karl Rove. This man coined the term “axis of evil” to describe targets of the War on Terror. While reading (10 pts)",
        "The Pet Goat to schoolchildren, this man was informed that a second plane had hit the Twin Towers. The 9/11 attacks took place under, for ten points, what 43rd President of the United States?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "George W. Bush",
        "Bush 43 before “43rd” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Alfred Einstein was the foremost 20th century biographer of this composer, whose 26th piano concerto was played at the coronation of Leopold II. This composer’s works are collected in the (20 pts)",
        "K¨ochel catalog, whose final numbered entry is his Requiem. As a child, this (10 pts)",
        "prodigy toured Europe with his sister Nannerl and father Leopold. For ten points, name this composer of the Jupiter symphony and operas like The Marriage of Figaro and The Magic Flute."
      ],
      "answer": "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Eugenics research was once carried out at what is now this island’s Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory. In an August 1776 battle, fighting took place on this island at the Rockaway Foot Path and Jamaica Pass. The first (20 pts)",
        "Levittown was created in this island’s Nassau County. The 1938 New England Hurricane destroyed dozens of seaside estates in the (10 pts)",
        "Hamptons on this island. A namesake sound separates Connecticut from, for ten points, what island that is home to Queens and Brooklyn?"
      ],
      "answer": "Long Island"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Sarah Bradford wrote a book titled Scenes in the Life of this woman and returned all the proceeds to fund her activism. While serving as a scout under James (20 pts)",
        "Montgomery, this woman led a successful raid on Combahee Ferry. This woman was asked to participate in an attack on a (10 pts)",
        "Virginia armory by an abolitionist, but was too sick to attend. For ten points, name this woman nicknamed “Moses” who “never lost a passenger” while helping slaves escape on the Underground Railroad."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Harriet Tubman",
        "Araminta Ross"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A nationalist in this city assassinated Kurt Eisner, a Jewish socialist who had earlier overthrown the local monarch. In 1972, members of Black (20 pts)",
        "September murdered several Israeli athletes during the Olympics hosted in this city. Inspired by the March on Rome, an uprising in this city flew the “Blood Flag” after leaving a (10 pts)",
        "beer hall. Adolf Hitler led an insurrection in, for ten points, what Bavarian city where Neville Chamberlain declared “peace for our time” after a 1938 meeting?"
      ],
      "answer": "Munich"
    }
  ]
}